<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both Houses of Parliament,</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52211747</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52211747</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2740:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both Houses of Parliament,</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by the Heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to the Kings most sacred Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With royal coat of arms on title page.</note>
                  <note>Speech discusses general current political situation, mentioning in particular the Popish Plot and current foreign policy.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175563:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <p>His Majeſties GRACIOUS SPEECH To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, <date>On <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 21<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1680.</date>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Sacred <hi>Majeſty,</hi> Anno <hi>DOM.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175563:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Gracious SPEECH to both Houſes of Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeveral Prorogations I have made, have been very advantageous to Our neighbours, and very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Me; for I have employed that time in making and perfecting an Allyance with the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſuitable to that which I had before with the States of the <hi>United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> and they alſo had with <hi>Spain,</hi> conſiſting of mutual obligations of ſuccour and defence.</p>
            <p>I have all the reaſon in the world to believe, that what was ſo much deſired by former Parliaments, muſt needs be very gratefull to you now; For, though ſome perhaps may wiſh theſe meaſures had been taken ſooner, yet no man can with reaſon think that it is now too late; for they who deſire to make theſe Allyances, and they who deſire to break them, ſhew themſelves to be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion: And as theſe are the beſt meaſures that could be taken for the ſafety of <hi>England,</hi> and the repoſe of Chriſtendom, So they cannot fail to attain their end, and to ſpread and improve themſelves farther, if Our diviſions at home do not render Our friendſhip leſs conſiderable abroad.</p>
            <p>To prevent theſe as much as may be, I think fit to renew to you, all the aſſurances which can be deſired, that nothing ſhall be wanting on My part, to give you the fulleſt ſatisfaction your hearts can wiſh, for the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion, which I am fully reſolved to maintain againſt all the Conſpiracies of Our Enemies, and to concur with you in any new remedies which ſhall be propoſed, that may conſiſt with the preſerving the Succeſsion of the Crown in its due and legal courſe of deſcent. And in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this, <hi>I</hi> do recommend it to you to purſue the further examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Plot, with a ſtrict and an impartial inquiry: I do not think my ſelf ſafe, nor you neither, till that Matter be gone through with; and therefore it will be neceſſar, that the Lords in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175563:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->the Tower be brought to their ſpeedy Tryal, that Juſtice may done.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you what danger the City of <hi>Tangier</hi> is in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of what importance it is to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to preſerve it. I have wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mighty Charge and Expence ſent a very conſiderable Relief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But conſtantly to maintain ſo great a Force as that W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will require, and to make thoſe new Works and Fortificatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without which the place will not be long tenable, amounts t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vaſt a Sum, that without your ſupport, it will be impoſsible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Me to undergo it. Therefore I lay the matter plainly bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you, and deſire your advice and aſsiſtance.</p>
            <p>But that which I value above all the Treaſure in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and which <hi>I</hi> am ſure will give Me greater ſtrength and rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation both at home and abroad, than any Treaſure can do, is perfect union amongst Our ſelves. Nothing but this can reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Kingdom to that ſtrength and vigour which it ſeems to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loſt, and raiſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s again to that conſideration which <hi>Englan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath uſually had.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> have their eyes upon this Aſſembly, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their own happineſs or miſery, as well as Ours, will depend upon.</p>
            <p>If We ſhould be ſo unhappy as to fall into ſuch a miſunde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtanding amongſt Our ſelves, as would render Our Friendſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> unſafe to truſt to, it will not be to be wondred at, if Our Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſhould begin to take new Reſolutions, and perhaps ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be fatal to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
            <p>Let <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s therefore take care that We do not gratifie Our En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and diſcourage Our Friends by any unſeaſonable Diſpute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> If any ſuch do happen, the world will ſee it was no fault of Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for I have done all that was poſsible for Me to do, to keep you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peace while I live, and to leave you ſo when I die.</p>
            <p>But from ſo great Prudence and ſo good Affections as yours can fear nothing of this kind; but do rely upon you all, that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will uſe your beſt endeavours to bring this Parliament to a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and happy Concluſion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
